Well, good morning, and thank you for being available to the committee this
morning. I'm Simon Law, chair of the Health Committee.
You'll see members around the table.
It'd be great if you could please briefly introduce yourselves and then give a
short overview, and then we can move into questions.
We'll be here for 30 minutes this morning.
Yep.
Thank you.
Thanks. Morning, and thank you for the opportunity to appear before you today.
My name is Kevin Ross. I chair the New Zealand Artificial Limbs Service Board,
which is more commonly known as the ALS, and I also bring a personal perspective of
nearly 40 years with a family member living with limb loss and using prosthetic
services. Joining us today online is Corin Barrett, president of
the Amputee Federation of New Zealand, who not only brings the perspective of lived
experience with limb loss but is an advocate for the amputee and limb different
community of Aotearoa. And here in person is Dr.
Dawn Adea, a rehabilitation physician who practices with both Health New Zealand
and ALS in Auckland and nationally through telehealth.
Dawn also serves as Health New Zealand's nominee on the ALS board.
And we have Sean Gray, our chief executive officer at ALS.
So today we'd like firstly to provide an overview of the New Zealand Artificial
Limb Service, including our approach and model of care, how we're funded, and how
outcomes are assessed. This is intended to address the committee's overarching
questions. We'd then like to provide additional clarification on information about
ALS that the committee has earlier been presented with.
And finally, I'll briefly note recent developments as ALS explores opportunity to
strengthen service delivery. I'm planning to leave plenty of time for questions,
which we welcome.
ALS is an autonomous Crown entity established under the Artificial Limb Service Act
and is responsible to the Minister for Social Development.
Our primary purpose is to enable independent and productive lives for people who
need prosthetic and orthotic devices.
More specifically, we design, manufacture, repair, and maintain highly
individualized medical devices, upper and lower limb prosthetics and orthotics,
supported by a wraparound care model of rehabilitation and peer support.
It is an integrated, coordinated service approach that looks to remove siloed
thinking and support patients' needs throughout their entire rehabilitation
journey. It is important to note that amputees often have very complex needs.
The prosthetic device itself is only one component of an amputee's long-term needs,
and our service is often a lifetime relationship with those we care for.
ALS services are provided at 10 service centers nationwide, supported by 14
regional clinics and a mobile workshop, and are delivered by our 220-plus
strong expert workforce, which includes 13 medical specialists, 60
orthotists/prosthetists, 25 appliance technicians, 21
physio and occupational therapists, five nurses, and 120 peer support
volunteers.
All ALS services are delivered under service contracts with Health New Zealand and
ACC. Under those contracts, we currently provide prosthetic services to some
4,598 amputees, up from 4,389 in
2020, and orthotic services to 11,269 patients,
up from around 3,324 in 2020.
Our model of care, our funding, and the performance requirements attached to this
are all defined through the service contracts with ACC and Health New Zealand.
The obligations embedded in these contracts form the basis of our accountability
and our reporting framework.
We're a world leader in prosthetic 3D printing, with approximately 60% of the lower
limb prosthetic sockets now produced using advanced 3D printing technology.
This level of adoption is significantly higher than most international services and
is improving consistency, efficiency, and patient outcomes.
Additionally, we are active investing in our future digital enablement, supported
by strong organizational procedures with robust governance and clearly defined
business and clinical use cases for AI to enhance service delivery and improve
patients' outcomes.
We are regularly independently audited against World Health Organization standards,
contract requirements, allied health standards, and financial accountability
standards.
I'll now hand over to Sean, who will provide some extra insights on the information
that's previously presented to the committee.
Thanks, Kevin. Kia ora, everybody.
Firstly, I'd like to talk to you some insights in and around patient choice, around
our prosthetic service that was discussed previously.
What we hear from our service users is they want coordinated and connected
services. They want the right people at the right time across their rehabilitation
journey with us. This feedback has led to a continuum of care model that
extends beyond the provision of the prosthetic device itself, and it ensures
patients, both now and in the future needs, have the lifelong support for the
services that they need. A very important part of this is around patient choice,
and this is an integral part of our service specifications and supporting policies
and procedures that we have with our contracts with ACC and Health New Zealand.
We have agreed mechanisms in place for second opinion.
They include accessing multidisciplinary teams, the use of clinical buddy
arrangements, reviews by other prosthetists or specialists within the center, and
referred to other centers as appropriate, and we can also access some external
specialist expertise when it's required.
For the highly specialized or complex cases where we have need for support,
we may access national experts and/or international experts, depending on the
patient's needs.
Also, we're in the early stages of developing subcontracting
relationships within our contract structures for accessing second opinion and
clinical services for them to provide.
This is via a fee for service arrangement.
We will give existing caseload, send second opinion referrals through.
We're also planning on supporting them by allowing access to our professional
development efforts, which are substantial, and also using our patient management
system to ensure that we have all the information required for the contracting
management.
Ultimately, the decision regarding referrals outside of the contract for prosthetic
services sits with ACC and Health New Zealand.
A few other things to note in and around the market that we operate in.
We operate in the competitive rehabilitation, disability, and injury markets.
These are government-funded in the prosthetic and orthotic side of things with
procurement is through open and competitive tendering processes, with one recent
exception. We compete alongside private providers for these allied health and
rehabilitation contracts. We understand from ACC they have 20 listed
providers there from both prosthetists and orthotists to provide services in the
space that we operate.
A review of the government electronic tendering service shows that in the last 10
years, there were 10 orthotic service procurement opportunities and one national
prosthetic procurement opportunity.
These procurement opportunities allowed all eligible providers with the opportunity
to participate fully and compete for the government work.
Across these opportunities, we were awarded seven contracts where ACC
assessed us, along with Health New Zealand, as the most appropriate provider
against the published procurement criteria.
Importantly, none of our service contracts provide ALS with exclusivity
rights.
The second thing I'd like to touch on relates to the comments in and around
workforce workload and caseload, and how that might relate to patient wait times.
Firstly, when we run a business in the areas of service delivery, there is always a
challenging balance between responsiveness, quality, workforce capability, and
funding. Our staffing levels are based on the contract specification
requirements, service demand, and complexity of the clinical caseload.
We also benchmark these numbers against things like the World Health Organization
standard, and then apply our local expertise in and around scope of practice to
normalize or understand what those numbers mean for what we need for service both
now and into the future.
Managing workloads in this area of healthcare is inherently complex.
Each patient's journey is often different, often involving multiple appointments,
involving customized devices that are manufactured for the individual, and a range
of health professionals.
We focus on maximizing our time on direct clinical care and rehabilitation outcomes
while seeking to improve efficiencies and value for money for our funders with
streamlined processes and improvements in our software, including cybersecurity
posture and the other related compliance that we need to ensure safe data
management.
Specifically, in and around the triage process, we've got an activity regarding
urgency and standard appointments.
Urgent appointments can be scheduled within two working days with our service with
the next available prosthetist. This might not always be the patient's usual
prosthetist. And also our system shows that from the time of appointment being
created, on average, through to the appointment being provided via special
services, an average of 11 working days.
This takes into account amputee and clinical team availability.
There are some cases where appointments can take longer, and this usually relates
to things like scheduling support for people with complex health needs and
wellbeing circumstances,
staff leave and sickness. Some stock issues can sometimes come in, and there are
also sometimes challenges in and around the manufacturing process that need to be
worked out for the individual's device.
We recognize that long wait times can affect the person's wellbeing, their work,
their ability to be independent, and mobilize.
Where delays are significant for the person, we encourage them to contact us so we
can review their circumstances. Sorry, sir?
Oh, no. I just wanted to move on to questions, please.
Mm.
And so we'll do that soon. So like, we could've had all of this in writing and read
through it.
All right.
It's good to have the overview, but I know members, and I've seen hands going up
already-
Excellent
... have some questions. So just to utilize the time.
We can't go any longer because we've got-
Understood
... 20 odd minutes. But I noticed there that, so you're saying that amputees are
free to access alternative providers, and therefore have a choice of provider.
But OIA information shows that only a small number of amputees have actually
received public funding to access an alternative provider.
Can you explain to the committee exactly how an amputee who is dissatisfied with
ALS's services can exercise a genuine choice to use an alternative
provider while retaining public funding?
There's two parts to that question.
Firstly, we are contracted to provide a specific service, and we have internal
second opinion capability on that front.
Regarding being referred to alternate providers, we are in the stages of developing
a subcontractor arrangement. This activity was done before this question came to
the committee. The health funding side of things for prosthetics services is being
underfunded, and we've worked well with Health New Zealand to resolve those
matters, which now puts us in a position to subcontract second opinion.
But ultimately, the decision for ACC and Health New Zealand whether an alternate
provider is given-
Okay
... sits with them.
So it sits with ACC and Health New Zealand.
Yeah.
And I-
We're trying to do our bit within our service to provide choice.
Yes. That lead me on to another question.
So if you've got a patient who's dissatisfied or has disagreements with their
provider or with their clinician, is there a funded pathway for them to obtain an
independent clinical assessment from a prosthetist who is not employed by a
contractor to, or accountable to ALS, with that assessment being publicly funded?
That question is one for ACC and Health New Zealand.
We're not in a position to answer on their behalf.
Okay. I saw Ingrid and Asha also had their hands up.
Thanks very much. What I guess we have heard is that there is an effective monopoly
on the service, and then what I've heard today is that you're a state-formed
entity, and there are some potential competitors who are not state-formed.
I heard that your accountability lies in the contracts, and I'm very interested in
that because we see with a lot of Health New Zealand contracts in particular, that
there are kind of output measures rather than outcomes.
Is it possible for us to see a copy of the indicators in the contract that you have
to reach for the performance measures?
And then secondly, with the fee for service on the subcontracting that you've
mentioned, is that a user pays type system?
Who will pay for that subcontracted service?
Is it coming from yourself or from the end user?
So to answer your first question, we can make the reports available to you.
I forward reports to ACC and Health New Zealand, and that-
It's more the indicators.
Okay.
If we could just see what the indicators are that you report to.
Yep.
Thank you.
I can give you one specific example-
Yep
... around the prosthetic delivery time frames.
And so within there, we do an 80% delivery time excluding consumables, and that's
three working days on average. When you look at all prosthetic types, it's around
about 12 working days.
Right.
There are reasons why they can take longer, because sometimes people need a
continual activity to provide, you know, the component steps involved.
And then the second part was around the subcontractor part, and who pays for that
service?
So at the moment, that service is intended that we will be paying for it.
It'll be going through our patient management system, where the subcontractor party
will be set up with a location, so they will only see their patients that we've
referred through to them. We need to give them a caseload so they can keep currency
with their practice. And then the second part of that is the refer through to
second opinion.
Okay, quickly, sup, just on that. That, so will you be clip- clipping the ticket on
that? My question.
There will be an administrative charge on at the moment.
We've got an hourly rate, because we've agreed to, and we've got an hourly rate
with ACC and Health New Zealand.
Yep.
I'll go Asha, then Alastair, Tam.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. I have a number of questions, but fortunately the first bunch
are just yes, no answers. I'm looking at your 2025 annual report.
Measuring their patient feedback, how well did we set you up to be independent and
productive in your community and at home?
You set yourself a, or you were set a target of 85%, but that was exceeded,
and 95% of service users reported that that target was met. Is that correct?
Yes.
And this one, how would you rate the overall service you received for the job we
have undertaken for you? The target was 85%, but that was exceeded at 94%.
Is that correct?
Correct.
And I see this one, how, which is very important, how would you score
the comfort of your artificial limb or orthoses at the moment?
The target was 70%, and it was 89% that the users reported.
Is that correct?
I'll need to double-check on that one.
To me, I did wonder why 70% was chosen for
that target. But anyway, so if you could come back to us on that, that'd be
appreciated.
Good point on that one. There's no benchmarks on that.
Yep.
The measure of the prosthetic socket comfort score is a verified outcome measure.
Uh-huh.
There's no benchmarking data available globally.
Thank you. You mentioned in your introductory remarks that you compare yourself to
WHO standards. Could you explain what the sorts of things that you're required
to look at there, and how, overall how the performance compares
to those World Health Organization standards?
So the, we've audited ourselves to the World Health Organization standards for
prosthetic and orthotic services.
Uh-huh.
They are a standard that's been developed and applied around the world.
They look at service delivery, user group, workforce allocation, quality standards,
et cetera, about how you're going.
This is not something that we are required to do by any of our service contracts.
We do it because we know we're in a privileged position with national contracts and
would like to ensure that we've got appropriate information to share with the
committees like this. If you'd like copies of that audit, it was done by Health New
Zealand. We can easily share it with you.
So when I look at these figures, to me it says that, you know, performance has
been exceeded in the last year. And in your comments, you provided some
commentary, some idea of how those people who aren't having a good
outcome can get second opinions or, um...
And so I'm just interested- Now that I'm reassured we're talking about a
minority, but for whom this will be the biggest issue in their life, and it
deserves to be taken seriously. What's their
journey through your service like, and where do you see improvements should be
made?
So with that, I might kick to Dawn to give a comment, and then pass to Corin if
it's all right.
Yeah. So obviously second choice is important. It's a normal part of patient care.
Already existing within ALS is a second opinion pathway, that happens
informally through a buddy system between clinicians.
It happens formally within a multidisciplinary team meeting.
It occurs between clinicians within center, it occurs between clinicians
nationally across our workforce, and there are times where we get external
expertise. So there's a range of opportunities within second opinion already within
service. We also have a number of medical specialists who support those second
opinions as well, from orthopedic surgeons, both in pediatric and adult, as well as
rehabilitation medicine specialists, as well as GPs too, amongst that
multidisciplinary team approach.
So, I think second opinion within service is already well established and existing.
ALS is on a continuous improvement pathway.
Always looking to do things better internally.
It might be helpful to hear from Corin. Corin.
Good morning. Yes. So, obviously, in my role
with the Amputees Federation, I am advocating on behalf of all
amputees. And I have found that,
I wouldn't consider it a minority, but there are complex issues
within the system and with amputees, and it's very difficult to please
everyone.
I am obviously a service user of ALS,
as a quad amputee. So I have been on the receiving end of
the service. But I also have a very open and frank
relationship with Shaun. And so I'm often the person
who's receiving the phone calls or the in-person
conversations with amputees that are frustrated, whether
it's the service or their limb or-- And there's a whole lot of
factors that need to be considered.
It's not just--
Often it could be a clash of personality.
It could be a
stage of the journey that they're on regarding
what their needs are, and that they feel that they're not being met.
Or I've had a limb for-
Mm-hmm
... 17 years, and now suddenly I'm having all these troubles.
But when you dig deep, you find that there's other health issues going on and
things like that. So it's very complex, it's very individualized.
But I do find I can pick up the phone and I can call either the
manager of the center or the clinician or talk to Shaun.
And Shaun is very willing to offer his phone number.
He's always willing to talk to the person directly.
And sometimes they don't want to
go to that level. So I'm kind of the middleman, so to speak.
But, yeah, it's
a big bucket of complexities and,
yeah, I can understand the frustrations from all sides.
Thank you. I'll go over to Carlus and then Ken.
I just want to say thank you. And congratulations on the opening on the Auckland
Center and show me around the workshop as well. I experienced it firsthand myself.
Thank you for all the stuff, for all the work you do. I talked to a few patient.
They actually saying that I'm making a huge difference to their life, so well done.
So I think during that visit, I think one of the issues we talked about was how to
shorten the production time. Is there anything government can do or we can open up
the logistical to import market for parts so we can speed up for the production for
the artificial limb?
Yeah, that's a key part of service satisfaction does relate to delivery times in
the manufacturing process. One of the things that we've done recently is the 3D
printing side of things. That's 60% of our lower limb sockets now.
And the cost of the printers that we'd like to use are in the half a million to $1
million. So we don't have the volume to justify ownership at this stage, and that
leads to about a two-week additional delivery time.
There are some intermediary things we can do with cheek sockets and things, but
ultimately that would be the single best thing we could have.
Can you also give a little bit more detail to the committee?
Because when I visit there, there's a new technologies guys working on, say, more
sensory. So you can use the hand to allow extra movement on the artificial limb.
And I think this is the time you say that this, the price, can be major issues for
the patient to choose to use it. Can you tell us what's the difference on the
price?
The price differences can be quite considerable.
A hand like this from INNERS, it's $36,000 or something along those lines.
This is actually a Taska hand from a company in Christchurch.
It's a great success story. We helped them with some of the commercialization in
that. But they can go up to $100,000 plus.
And that's just for the hand arrangement.
If you want to use a elbow joint, I think they're about $75,000, and that's because
the arm codes in America have it at that.
I think the build costs are way cheaper to your point.
And then when you put in a thing called pattern recognition, which is sensory
things that can go on a chest or the stump, they need to be individualized to the
person. They need to be trained how to use them so they can do things like control
the sensors on the inside to open and close it, and move the elbow up and down.
Thank you. Ken.
Well, first-
Go to Carlus
... I've got a question on that. Just listening to what you've said so far, you've
got multiple service providers in the market.
Mm-hmm.
Trying to increase choice. You're dealing with subcontractors, you're competing for
contracts, you're getting external expertise.
I'm wondering why do you still need to be a Crown entity?
That's a really good question, and I think it's fair to say over the last 10 years
we've been challenging that and speaking to the ministers involved.
And at this stage it is under active consideration.
We're giving a five-year legislative review, so it's an issue that's right before
everybody right at this moment.
Okay.
Awesome.
So that's-
No.
Okay. We have a few more questions, but cognisant of Carl's going off.
If it's all right, I might fire the-- Well, I'll get some of those sent through to
you. But want to say thank you very much for making yourselves available for the
committee this morning. Thank you.
No, we appreciate it. Thanks again.
Chance to talk.
Thanks, Corin.
Thank you.
So much, Corin.